{
  "reference_number": "18",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With a \"force majeaure\" caveat - as it is impossible to predict what is going to happen in the next 30 years and and there is every\n\n possibility that targets may have to be brought forward or increased/decreased as new science dictates."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Sensible to keep an eye on the future with an achievable phased plan for the immediate next 5 yrs"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Again, there must be a provision to amend the Bill as we are now into uncharted territory and so there has to be some flexibility to\n\n allow for unexpected events. Given the huge volatility we are dealing with - there can be no certainty of outcome - the only thing that\n must be cast in stone is the obligation to adhere to the worlds highest standards and accepted best practices"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Definition of exceptional standards - needs to be defined - either force majeure or to allow for improvements to new best standards\n or scientific updates that demand more urgent action"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I notice that one of the elements missing is any strategy for greening up our urban areas. This is an essential element of any carbon\n\nreduction plan. Melbourne has one, Sydney has one, France, the Netherlands, UK, Canada, Singapore. NZ needs an Urban Greening\nStrategy to ensure resilient, healthy cities for future generations. This links in to water run-off management, urban temperatures, air\n\nquality, stress reduction, mental health, obesity, etc etc.... Hanging Gardens of NZ would be delighted to work with you on this"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Not sure - but it seems logical to have the governance under one roof"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Urban greening expertise must be included."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Essential - we are already in the process of having to adapt to climate change and this will be a critical element we have to deal with in\nthe near future"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think this is a fantastic and well researched document which makes an important first step. Congratulations! In order for this to be of\n\nmaximum benefit - we need to ensure a high proportion of NZ people engage with it. This requires a lot of targeted marketing - This\nneeds a very strong Stakeholder and Communications Management Strategy. A great job and well done . I would welcome any further\ndiscussions on the subject"
    }
  ]
}
